<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>FDA Blog</title>
<link>https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>A Collection of Works About Functional Data Analysis (FDA)</description>
<generator>quarto-1.5.54</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Functional Features for Time Series</title>
  <dc:creator>Santiago Rodriguez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/posts/functional-features/post.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="about" class="level1">
<h1>About</h1>
<p>This work is exploratory and currently unfinished. The purpose of the work is to assess if features created using functional data analysis are useful. The work was inspired by <a href="https://github.com/hendersontrent/catch22">Catch22</a>.</p>
<p>As far as I am aware, this is novel research.</p>
<p>The following is a description from the Catch22 GitHub repo:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Catch22 is a collection of 22 time-series features coded in C that can be run from Python, R, Matlab, and Julia. The catch22 features are a high-performing subset of the over 7000 features in hctsa</p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="details" class="level1">
<h1>Details</h1>
<p>I’ve been working and learning about functional data analysis on and off for the past three years. Over the course of this time I learned about Catch22 and other works(<a href="https://github.com/benfulcher/hctsa">hctsa</a>, <a href="https://github.com/hendersontrent/theft">theft</a>, <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/feasts/index.html">feast</a>).</p>
<p>Much of my work focused on analyzing energy consumption data. During this time I learned that the deriatives of energy consumption were helpful to gain a more complete understanding of consumption patterns. The derivatives are velocity and accelartion.</p>
<p>With functional data analysis it’s trivial to estimate the velocity and accerlation of a smooth curve fitted to the data. I thought that summarizing these derivatives into features would be helpful/ predictive.</p>
</section>
<section id="analyses" class="level1">
<h1>Analyses</h1>
<p>The first step is to evaluate if the functional features are <em>significant</em>. I will attempt to assess this by comparing the functional features agains features from existing libraries. This is a <a href="">link</a> to the code.</p>
<p>If the funcitonal features are found to be predictive, then a subsequent step would be to produce a package so others can test the features for themselves.</p>
<section id="attempt-1" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="attempt-1">Attempt 1</h2>
<p>This work is ongoing.</p>
<p><strong>Progress:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>step 1: evaluation of functional features: work in progress</li>
<li>step 2: create a package</li>
</ul>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/posts/functional-features/post.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The Power of Functional Data Analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Santiago Rodriguez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/posts/the-power-of-fda/post.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The work should be visible below. If it isn’t please clink this (<a href="https://kaladin-stormblessed.quarto.pub/the-power-of-functional-data-analysis/">link</a>).</p>
<section id="introduction" class="level1">
<h1>Introduction</h1>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The objectives of this article are threefold: to provide a gentle, non-technical introduction to functional data analysis, demonstrate an application using functional data analysis to make inferences about customer behavior, and showcase how such inferences can be leveraged as features in other processes, such as predictive models.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="{=html}">
<iframe src="https://kaladin-stormblessed.quarto.pub/the-power-of-functional-data-analysis/" width="100%" height="700px">
</iframe>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Residential</category>
  <guid>https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/posts/the-power-of-fda/post.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Novel Approach to Define the Peak Hours of Consumption for Individual Customers and Groups of Customers Using Functional Data Analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Santiago Rodriguez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/posts/peak-hours/post.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The work should be visible below. If it isn’t please clink this (<a href="https://rpubs.com/kaladin_stormblessed/onpeak_fda">link</a>).</p>
<section id="abstract" class="level1">
<h1>Abstract</h1>
<p>The following text was obtained from the publication.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>A common analysis in utilities is the use of meter read data to define peak hours of consumption. This paper proposes a novel approach using functional data analysis (FDA) to define the peak hours of consumption for individual customers and groups of customers. Through functional data analysis, smooth, differentiable curves are fitted to an individual customer’s meter read data. Then, the individual on-peak times are aggregated to define on-peak hours for a group of customers, such as for all residential customers.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The individual customer on-peak hours are proposed as the times of day where the velocity or the rate of change is greatest or least, respectively. The group on-peak hours are determined by two different methods; the first by assessing the distributions of the start and end aggregated individual on-peak windows and the second via an unsupervised statistical learning procedure.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="{=html}">
<iframe src="https://rpubs.com/kaladin_stormblessed/onpeak_fda" width="100%" height="700px">
</iframe>
</div>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>Residential</category>
  <category>Research</category>
  <guid>https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/posts/peak-hours/post.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2022 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Estimated Consumption via Functional Data Analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Santiago Rodriguez</dc:creator>
  <link>https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/posts/ce-estimated-consumption/post.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>The work should be visible below. If it isn’t please clink this (<a href="https://rpubs.com/kaladin_stormblessed/CMS_FDA">link</a>).</p>
<p><strong>Summary provided by an <em>AI</em></strong></p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The publication presents a method for estimating electricity consumption using Functional Data Analysis (FDA). The author applies FDA techniques to model patterns over time, leveraging the flexibility of R’s <code>fda</code> packages.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="{=html}">
<iframe src="https://rpubs.com/kaladin_stormblessed/CMS_FDA" width="100%" height="700px">
</iframe>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Commercial</category>
  <guid>https://saintrod.github.io/fda-blog/posts/ce-estimated-consumption/post.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
